okay uh hello everyone uh U we organize
these uh we we are hting dday today uh
we organize these monthly events to talk
about tech or the problems or the things
that interest Community uh in in their
day-to-day life or day-to-day work so
today we are going to talk about uh Java
link virtual threats uh baves is the
speaker he's been working with since
past one year and he has almost eight
years of experience in the domain that
he's working in so most of you must have
heard about Java 21 right
so yeah so this is this is the topic
also if if you are interested in some
topic that you have knowledge on and you
want to share with some Community uh
we'll be happy to host you just give us
that talk detail we can make that happen
okay okay all lat here part of the J
sorry this will be the part of the J yes
this will be uh like first uh session in
the jvm series uh there will be more
many more sessions on the jvm but yeah
this is the first session on the jvm
series so stick along if you want to
learn more on the
JM cool uh we can get started uh I think
I'm audible to audience
on uh online
basically am
I yeah
awesome okay uh so hi everyone as I
mentioned my name is baves so today's
talk is mostly on the virtual thread uh
virtual thread is basically the Oracle
guys has done a good job uh in last five
years basically they have introduced
this part of java 21 released it uh the
first introduction happened as part of
java 19 then the second preview was
released as part of java 20 and now
finally it is released so we'll go over
it and understand how we should use use
it um what are benefits of moving
towards virtual thread when should we
use it and how it works
internally so yeah this is the agenda
for today's talk uh we'll go through the
need of
concurrency understand thread for rec
style limitation of native threads and
then the ways to overcome limitations
and then uh discuss about Loom virtual
versus platform threads how it works
internally adoption guide and then at
the end we can take the questions and
feedback okay uh need of
concurrency uh so can anyone tell me
what is the need of concurrency
uh maybe let's make that this talk
interactive and you can also speak up if
you have anything to say yeah uh to
execute multiple task right uh at
multiple times uh so it's a kind of a uh
worker model right whereas a task has to
be done with parallel things say
parallel say suppose to be done by
threads right yeah but what is the need
of executing things parall so it will
reduce the uh execution time right if it
is taking 10 minutes if you are using
concurrency there are chances that it
will take some 5 minutes or something
like that basically time optimization
yeah right so one thing is to utilize
the CPU properly uh we don't want CPU to
be idle and as you mentioned uh that to
fulfill the need of modern application
we mostly know that the uh modern
application requires high throughput on
low latency and today we are going to
Target high throughput in the
stock okay uh let's take this stock with
the one example uh of thread per request
style so thread per request style model
basically talks about uh assigning one
thread for request this is mostly your
typical web
application works this way whenever you
get one any request you will assign one
thread for that particular entire
request and then that particular request
will be responsible to execute entirely
right so here we have one uh API called
recommend products basically one method
where we are passing One customer ID and
this particular uh API Returns the
product recommended for that customer uh
here we are doing three operation one is
we are getting the customer we are
catching the customer preference we are
catching the orders and then we are
preparing the recommendation and then
returning it if there is nothing to
return then we returning the empty list
uh anyone wants to talk about what are
the pro what pros and cons you can see
when you look at the
code anything that you find that okay
this is good something which you find
weird some scaling
issues okay so if we talk about good
part you can see that this code is
simple enough to understand all right
simple enough to reason about because
you know the flow goes from top to
bottom you first fetching the customer
then you're fetching the customer
preference order service and then the uh
preparing the product recommendation so
for example something goes wrong in any
of those particular
call that we are making you know that
the flow will be stopped at that point
of
time also it is easier to test and
easier to read right uh but do you think
this is scalable code I'll tell you for
example let's say this fetch customer
service and these all three calls which
are we are doing is an external call so
we are calling the other service to
fetch the customer detail we are calling
some other service to fet the customer
preference and finally fet the order
history
so assume that order history takes 1
second uh to get response the customer
preference takes around 500 milliseconds
and this takes around 400 milliseconds
and we just require only 50 milliseconds
in order to prepare the product
recommendation so entirely we are
waiting for
1.95 seconds to to return the response
right uh any answer like how can we
improve
this
we
use
okay
okay so and and what is the uh problem
with this code so thread per request
style basically governs by little law so
ler loss tells that okay a throughput is
basically your behaves from in terms of
number of concurrency divide by latency
so for example let's say if you have 10
concurrent requests which is being
processed in 50 milliseconds it means
your application is able to process 200
request per second right uh if you want
to increase throughput then what are the
ways either you need to increase the
number of concurrent request that you
can support or you need to decrease the
latency now uh for example lat if we
talk about the external calls the
latency is not in your hand um you might
not be able to change the latency
because it's somebody else's service and
you don't have control over it so one
way to increase the request is by
basically increasing the or support
supporting the number of concent
requests right so for example if you
have to uh support 100 request uh if you
have to increase the throughput to 200
200 2,000 request per second you need at
least 100 uh request con request need to
be supported here if you want to
increase to 20,000 it will go to 10,000
if you increase more and go to 1
million or 2 million request per second
it means you
need 100,000 request to be supported
concurrently now uh what's the problem
with the with that so um the limitation
can we do that like can we
create 100,000
threads because we we said that okay the
uh in thread per request style we assign
one thread to process the entire request
so when we are saying that we need to if
we are want to increase the throughput
of the application at least we need to
have those many number of threads
created and they need to serve the
request so you guys might know that
creating those many threads are not
practical uh and the reason is basic of
basically the limitation of platform
threats So jvm So currently the native
threads that we are having those threads
are basically thin wrapper around the
kernel or the oos thread so whatever you
assign to that those particular jvm
thread is basically being hand over to
the kernel thread and kernel thread
performs the operation uh so if there is
any blocking call it means your kernel
thread is going to be
blocked right also the the threads
basically uh when you create a thread so
typically on uh
x64 machines it takes 1 MB of size stack
size and on x86 machine takes around 512
KB of a stack size so for example if you
are creating millions or 100,000 threads
imagine the size that you require in
order to create those number of
threads right uh then that's only the
stack size then you have the Heap size
as well so you need a massive machine to
at least support
it
uh then the high memory foot okay the
thread creation is also expensive it
just okay for example let's say for some
reason you you are able to create th000
or 100,000 threads but the time it takes
to create a thread is also a heavy
operation also the context switching
right so when you have to switch there
many threads uh the time it takes is
huge so that's why we cannot create so
that's why like we don't have option to
create as many threads as we want uh so
what are the ways to solve this things
so people has come up with the ideas of
for example creating a thread pool so in
thread pool what you typically do is you
create some amount of threads uh for
example
tomates 200 threads by default and then
you create number of tasks and assign
those tasks to those thread pools so
then thread pool basically assign
whichever thread is uh available it will
pick up any task from the queue and
start processing it but now what's the
problem with the thread poing so in
thread pooling you only have The Limited
number of requ threads so for for
example if you have 200 threads so at a
time and if your task is a blocking task
right you are doing you are making a
call which is like external call and it
is basically a blocking call then what
happens is uh 200 threads let's say even
in from the 200 threads if 30 or 40
threads are blocked it means you wasting
some
CPU because the threads are blocked uh
it cannot perform anything else and if
let's say all the 200 threads are
blocked and if you have massive load
then in that Cas B your service will um
not perform well so those are the
scaling issue that we see with the
thread pooling so then what is the
solution so as you mentioned that okay
we can also use the completable future
or future basically un synchronous way
of handling things so there are two
things we can do in terms of unson style
so earlier we used to do async blocking
what is async blocking so for example we
had this particular flow of
uh the U execution so we you were
fetching the order then the customer
preference or the customer and they were
taking basically this amount of time 1
second 5 milliseconds 400 milliseconds
and then the 50 milliseconds in total it
was taking 1.95 Mill seconds so if you
want to improve it one way to do is
basically you call fetch order and Par
you call fetch customer preference and
the fetch customer so here while the
fetch order is in progress you will be
able to fetch the other two things and
then construct the response so in total
it goes around 1.05 seconds uh here you
are when you are saying a sync blocking
what it means is you are creating three
different threads or assigning this task
to three different threads to fetch this
um data and then construct the response
right so essentially here you have
better approach but still you are
blocked for that particular time and uh
you are wasting some of the uh CPU there
so if we then the next thing that we can
okay the the solution for or the
optimization that happened on top of
this is coming up with the non-blocking
stack so then people has come up with
the non blocking stack you might know uh
for example Java has um introduced nio
stack similarly there are many other
languages which are using the
non-blocking stack uh non-blocking stack
is basically when what we are doing in
non-blocking is your request or your
thread itself is not blocked what means
is whenever the fetch order request is
made the request will be unblocked
immediately and the the call will be
given to the channels uh channels to
process or take it forward so basically
there is some one thread or some thread
basically which are making that call but
your framework threads are uh not
blocked what it means is that it's
mostly now it event based U
communication so whenever you get a
request your thread makes that call call
and then uh immediately it gets freed
similarly when we are making this call
that thread will again thread will make
a call and immediately it will be freed
and then we'll wait we'll do some other
operation so that is a synchronous
nonblocking way of handling things so
here if you are having millions or
hundred or thousands of threads
basically you your thread pull will able
to handle those requests what it will do
is it will basically pick one request if
there is any asynchron or any blocking
call it will immediate it will call that
particular thing and immediately uh free
up and then we'll be able to process the
other request so that is asynchronous
non-blocking
but okay uh this comes with its own
challenges people had to develop this
non-blocking not because it's easy but
as we Face there is a issue with or
there are challenges with the
synchronous we have doing things when
you are blocking you are not able to
scale up properly and that's why uh
people had to develop this non-blocking
stack around uh with
uh yeah so um when you look at the code
right so what are the challenges so
challenges are one is it's no longer
simpler so when you read a code it is
not when you look at the non-blocking
code basically it's you might have seen
the completable future code where you
are doing or composing things uh so it
it is not that simple to understand to
or read or to reason about for example
if these three things are going or
happening in
what if something goes wrong in customer
preference will it um terminate the
execution here or the fet customer call
Will Go
On um also it will be hard to understand
the what is the uh stack Trace when you
like take a thread down you will not get
the usable context around the uh stack
traces debugging and profiling become
hards uh so when you try to debug or
even you test it it becomes harder than
the synchronous code that we
saw uh so essentially the application
unit of concurrency is no longer
platform unit platform's unit of
concurrency so the reasoning of cod
becomes harder when you move to the
nonblocking
stack so
to U solve the problem of a synchronous
or basically to solve the problem of
synchronous um way of doing things for
example issue and to help to make your
code uh look s same as the synchronous
code the virtual thread has uh done a
good job there so here what uh has
happened is so virtual thread is
basically nothing but your user defined
threads so for example you can see here
so these threads will be created within
the jvm and these threads are mapped on
to your platform threads so it's now
responsibility or it basically jvm is in
control of creation and scheduling of
these threads onto a platform
threads U
so here it is not one to one mapping but
rather one thread can be mapped onto any
of this platform thread which is also
called as a carrier thread and then
those particular threads are being again
executed for example these are nothing
but the kernel
thread so
one benefit here is it's cheap to create
what it means is only few bytes 100
bytes basically um are U required in
order to create this particular virtual
thread so you can infinite you can
thetically create infinite number of um
virtual threads because it's not taking
that much amount of
memory also it's very fast to create uh
jvm handles the life cycle and
scheduling because jvm handles the life
cycle and scheduling uh JV jvm has more
control over scheduling part jvm can
schedule it or unschedule it or park it
or unpark it based on the uh blocking
call that is
happening user thre request sty more
efficiently so now you can use the
thread per request style code which we
saw which is simple enough to understand
uh right and and test with that with the
same performance as the asynchronous way
of doing things okay can achieve same
scale as a asynchronous code does not
require learning New Concept this is
again one benefit is if you are moving
to Virtual thread you don't require to
learn New Concept like you have to learn
it for reactive stack or the
asynchronous
stack okay so let's understand how we
can create this uh virtual thread so
there is Executor service which is
introduced as part of
uh executors itself so new virtual
thread part task executor what it does
is basically it creates new virtual
thread every time uh you submit some
task to that executor so here we are
saying that okay for 0 to th000 for each
iteration we are creating new thread and
just giving this duration of sleep of 1
second uh you can run this as well it
works really
well uh we can now check the
code
uh you guys are able to see the screen
right
yeah
okay so if you see uh the same code is
here recommend products we have again
fetch
customer fetch customer preference order
history so if you want to so this is
basically your typical springbot
application
so if you want to enable or um use
Virtual thread on your existing spring
boot application so if you're using
spring boot uh before 3.1 do 3.2 dox
then uh okay let me
open all you need to do is you need
to uh create this beans and override the
existing executor for the Tomcat so here
you can say set executor and you can say
executor virtual thread per task
executor also you are doing the same
thing for the assing task executor you
are giving the basically uh giving the
new executor for the virtual thread how
we are doing here is basically we have
added
this property called thread executor
virtual so if it is virtual then we are
um creating a bin which will be used in
order to replace your underlying
executor service with the virtual
threads
no you need only one so if you are only
using the synchronous code then only one
but in case of a
sync any a sync operation right you need
both so it is recommended to do to
override for both the
protocol
this
basically virtual threads yes so Tom now
will use the executor virtual thread
full executor
service okay so now you were saying that
okay it's gives that uh the same kind of
throughput or scale as as sync
programming does but do we have
any uh
proof so well let's look at
it okay just give me a second I will
just so what I'm doing is I am um
starting this
application again uh I have commented
out this property so now the underlying
uh thread pool would be the normal
platform threads that Tom
uses and here we have if you see we have
test uh here what we are doing is we so
we will first start with the 100 threads
as Tomcat has like 200 default thread in
the thre pool so we are going going with
the
uh are you able
to okay I
think okay I'm not able to zoom here uh
give me a
minute okay let to
zoom for okay I will just um explain uh
if you are not able to say it so we have
100 number 100 user so we have given
that okay 100 parallel user needs to
access this particular endpoint uh for
30 seconds we will learn this test so we
have created this endpoint uh so
endpoint is the same which we
saw here basically okay let me
um so product recommendation service so
what we have done here is nothing but we
have induced some kind of sleep here
just to um simulate our experience for
blocking part so if you see here 500
millisecond of sleep is there 400
millisecond and then the 1 second so in
total it should take more than 1.9
second uh and then we are basically
calling calling that
endpoint 100 times with the 100
concurrent request okay let's run
this cool so uh if you see then the
request would start now we can see that
are request being made every
second and if you look at the sample
time which is below 2 second
are you guys able to see properly uh
no now so if you see uh the request time
is basically U within 2 second because
we we are only u in quaring I mean
sending 100 requ 100 request per second
so if
we look at the response
graph it's a constant time right it
didn't go up above the 200 seconds now
let's do one
thing let's say we we are increasing our
request to
th000 request per
seconds and let's see what would be
the let me okay
nice so you you can see the has
increased but if you look at the time
that it takes to process those request
right has increased as well Laten
see so it means your application is not
able to handle that load
yes because your request is basically
waiting your threats are waiting on
those blocking part so the new request
which are coming are skewed and that's
why taking a long time to process or
your
request so after 30 second if you look
at the
graph you can see the request are going
on and the time is
increasing if you look at the response
graph it's basically going
up right so this is the problem with the
um the threads the platform threads now
let's test it out with our U virtual
threads so I'll go here
uncommanded out and then run the
application
again here we'll clear the graph so you
you have seen graph right so basically
here it's it started with 6 second the
reason here is basically because of the
contention so for as it supports only
200 request per request at a time we are
giving thousand requests and because of
those requests there's a contention and
that's why why it takes a longer time to
process or to um uh complete your
request so we can clear
this application is up and with the same
load here we are G keeping the same load
1,000 request per second and we we are
running for the 30
second and if you look at the
response it is constant
within that 2
second same load we saw earlier that it
was taking a lot of time but now as we
move to Virtual threads it is within the
time limit that we are we were thinking
that okay it should take around 1.9
second not more than that
uh
right so after 30 second if we look at
the
graph it is constant
Chang same code yes we just change the
underlying executor service we are
saying that rather than using PL form
threads we need to we want to use now
virtual threads
yes awesome uh any question here or we
can go
next uh in this case why why is there a
downward print so it started the
Thousand request uh but then it was able
to catch up the load and then has it
going
down so when you when you start right
you create the threads right basically
you need to create virtual thread so
thread creation is also takes some some
time and that's why it's more than 1.9
seconds uh as you have many threads it's
already started to process it once it is
created being in use then it goes down
[Music]
okay cool
uh
so so we saw the uh performance as well
now let's understand how it is
implemented or how it works
internally right so basically virtual
thread are again implementation of java
length. thread uh so everything or all
the observability or if you say
monitoring tools which are there uh will
also be useful or work for the virtual
threads you can take the thread dump and
you can also monitor it um all the
support is also provided for the virtual
threads uh there are two main construct
to understand here continuation
scheduler so continuation is basically
again uh lowlevel API which um Java
doesn't I mean the Oracle doesn't
recommend to use in production so but
they are using the continuation in order
to achieve this and then there's a
Schuler which schedules the threats or
the task on the platform thread so what
happens
is uh when you assign or when you give
any task to a virtual thread virtual
thread will wrap that particular task
within a continuation and then and then
it the task will be given to the
uh so here by default U Fork joint pool
is being used for the scheduling part so
for here as we see uh in in terms of for
pool it uses the um default parallelism
is number is equal to number of your
Hardware threads for example the virtual
thread is being um carried on the worker
one so now what happens is whenever
there is a blocking call whenever
there's a blocking call the continuation
do yield will be called so this guys
have changed it's not uh that simple so
for example this guys has added or
changed the existing Java code in order
to understand the blocking calls so
whenever jvm finds any blocking call it
calls the yield method which essentially
puts your virtual thread which is
nothing but an object on your
hip so virtual thread basically contains
all the contexts it was running on so
let's say you were running some U
instruction and at some instruction you
are calling the blocking cord at at that
time basically that particular
instruction is also saved with the
context so whenever there is a data
available so what then what operating
system does is whenever there is a data
available it basically uh interrupts
gives a signal to your jvm which
internally interrupts or or calls the
continuation do run method continuation
run method is nothing again it runs or
it assigns that virtual thread to the
worker thread so for example if the same
thread was available then the same
thread will be able to um uh um carry
the virtual thread but let's say this
worker one is busy in some other task
then the virtual thread can be assigned
on the worker
to so the virtual thread can be uh
carried by any of the worker threads
because as it has the context where
it left earlier it can continue its own
work so that is how it works
internally uh any question so what
happens essentially is even though your
code looks synchronous but underneath
when Whenever there is a synchronous or
blocking call that jvm finds it replaces
that synchronous call with a sync stack
or nonblocking stack so then there is a
polar which basically PS the particular
non-blocking um operation and once it
gets the result then it's basically
assign that virtual thread back to the
uh a task basically back to the your
worker any of the worker thread and then
it can continue from there
so this is how it works internally we
now can discuss about the adoption guide
any question so
far so what will be the worker pool size
there in the for joint pool so by
default it is basically same as your
underneath Hardware threats for example
if you're using four cores it is four
but then you can also it can also grow
in size uh you can also configure
it okay yeah um uh so one thing I mean
if there are lot of uh
blocking uh virtual threads then they
would fill up the chances are that they
would fill up the Heap since so virtual
thread by okay so the size of virtual
threads are very small so one essential
thing is whenever you create a virtual
thread uh try to make sure that the your
task which you are creating is small
enough so it will just complete that
task and then die off so once that
virtual thread is die off your
garbage collector will clean
it okay yeah any recommended uh you know
time or uh something for a task to be
given to a virtual
thread no so it basically depends on
your use case uh ideally you should if
let's say if you're using um if you are
having any non-blocking call or sorry
blocking uh call then in that case you
need to make sure what time it takes to
complete the task right even though the
blocking Cod is fine but if you're
handling a lot of thing in one
particular task right which can grow for
example you're adding a lot of creating
a big objects within that particular
task itself which can grow indefinitely
then it's basically can create a inde
definite of we will also talk about it
like how we can avoid it but we need to
make sure that we are giving small task
so that it can die off and then clean it
um regularly okay uh so uh one more
thing what I understood from virtual
threads is uh it is another layer above
the jvm thread so right so virtual
threads uh would be given to the jvm
thre and jvm would give to the platform
threads so it's kind of an another layer
so uh I'm not able to understand that
how it is
reducing uh the overall time since it's
another layer and it's being I mean I
understand that it's the concept can be
that I take lot of tasks in a queue and
then just return back but the uh task or
is there uh in a queue and then I keep
pulling kind of a concept but I'm not
able to um understand that uh internally
maybe there would be some kind of an
implementation detail that even though
adding another layer to the jvm threads
it's still able to reduce the time so
that that is what I'm not able to
understand yet okay so as we saw what
are the ways to increase your concurrent
request or support the con right one is
either you have like infinite number of
threads so for each particular request
you assign a thread and then that thread
will be responsible to perform the
complete request right agreed yeah but
now your platform threads are having
issues uh of as we saw that basically
the memory footprint is high the thread
is time that it takes to create a thread
is high the the context s that happens
is very high and that's why it is not we
cannot create as many thread as we want
and that's why o also has some capping
over it right in terms of virtual thread
now as it is kind of an object simple
object uh so jvm can create 100 of those
small objects to uh accept that request
that you are sending to your application
so now rather than your threads or the
platform threads which are going to
accept the request directly the first it
will go to Virtual thread yeah thre will
handle it if it and if it sees that okay
the the request is basically spending a
lot of time in the blocking calls right
at that time it will say okay I am
blocked uh it will ask VIR the JM that
okay I'm I'm blocked and now you can
assign any other or assign the
underlying worker thread to M perform
some other task so in that case what we
are doing is we are yielding so the
virtual thread is basically yielding and
then it basically parked on the Heap H
okay the time it gets the data once the
we once the operating system sees that
there's a data uh which was requested by
this particular task uh it will again
put onto the uh worker thread so in that
way your underlying worker threads are
not blocked so example say if you have a
thread pool of 200 so those 200 threads
are not blocked they are able to perform
or they are able to uh take new task and
and and work on it yeah so uh but the
limitation of the platform I mean jvm
threads routing to platform threads that
is still there so if the platform thread
is blocked and uh virtual threads they
need to uh you know um uh give to the
jvm thread so and then if the platform
threads is anyways blocked uh the
virtual thread will still be stuck right
right right so that discuss again in the
adoption guide so when we disc the
adoption guide we will also discuss like
how we should adopt to it when we should
use it uh in what cases it will give the
benefit when we use the virtual threads
okay hey sorry to interrupt is the
session going to be recorded like uh I
need to leave the session so yeah it
will be streamed uh and also will be uh
we'll put it on YouTube
okay thank you
thanks okay so let's discuss about the
adoption guide so uh basically it is
recommended to use your normal uh
blocking way of doing or handling the um
things for example here uh it is
recommended to use thread per request St
what it means your one thread will be
using uh the or one thir will be
assigned to perform the your operation
for example here rather than going or
using the liable feature because here
then you are creating some different uh
threads and handling or um doing this
operation within it uh so benefit you
will not get that benefit for here
because it's already in in a synchronous
way so you will get benefit or see the
benefit of when you write your code in
um thread per request
style then never pull a virtual thread
so one recommendation is you should not
pull a virtual thread so as platform
thread are SC resource so it makes sense
to pull those particular threads and
that's why we pull platform threads but
as virtual threads
are very cheap to create and infinitely
plentiful uh you should not pull it or
you should not have a um pull of virtual
thread so the other reason is if you
start pulling it and if you are creating
a millions of virtual thread then your
HEAP will keep on
growing uh because then you are not um
removing those threats or those threats
are basically being used and and and
that's why it will never die
off though so when you say new virtual
thread per request task executor even
though it's a so in normal task executor
or normal executor service that you
might have seen there mostly your
creates the pool executor with the size
of some threads so basically it pulls
the thread but here it will every time
when we submit a task to this executor
it will create a new virtual thread and
assign that particular task to that
virtual
thread uh but what if you want to limit
the concurrency for example if you have
some use case where you want to do a
rate limiting or remit the concurrency
so in that case you can use some OS
level construct like SE 4 so sea 4
basically we saying that okay 10 only 10
uh concurrent request we want to allow
for this particular uh call call limited
service so here you can first acquire
then you call the service which she
which you need to do a limiting and then
you release the same for so at a time
only 10 concurrent requests will be
allowed to process or call this
particular endpoint or service or
API so that is one way to uh handle it
and now here it is mentioned that don't
cash expensive reusable objects uh so if
you so thread local basically works for
virtual thread as well so but it is
recommended not to cash those expensive
object the reason is here you can create
infinite number of threads right and
every time you create a new thread the
thread will also create a thread local
for example if you're using the
expensive objects within it if you are
caching it then it will also be there in
the Heap so your basically memory will
die off you will get the out of memory
issues or you need to have like a big
memory there so it is recommended not to
use the expensive not to cash expensive
U objects so here in this case there
there is a New Concept called scope
variable that is going to be released so
that is the scope variable is there as
part of preview uh you can take a look
at it um how it handles this uh or how
it basically provides the uh value or
provides the uh cachable objects to your
virtual
threads and then avoid lengthy and
frequent pinning so KV of using uh
virtual threads there are two kards one
is if you're let's say within a virtual
thread if you're making a native call
then virtual thread will be pinned onto
your underlying uh platform thread
because now jvm has no context what is
happening in your foreign function or in
your native function even if there is a
blocking call or non-blocking call J jvm
will have not any um understanding of
that so that's why it is not able to uh
unblock uh it is not able to park your
virtual thread Whenever there is a
native or the foreign call Point
function call
second uh kvart is the synchronized
block so whenever you are using a
synchronized block your virtual thread
is basically pinned onto your platform
thread uh so if your synchronized block
is just guarding some kind of a inmemory
object uh then it is fine even if your
synchronized block is not making kind of
a frequent blocking call or long
blocking calls which is still fine but
if it is like Len and the frequent
blocking call and if you are using
virtual threads then it will be pinned
onto your platform threads and there you
can see some scaling issue so what's the
solution here uh so in this case we can
use the re-entrant lock you can just say
lock create a object of reentrant lock
acquire it perform whatever the
operation you want to perform and you
can unlock it so this is the current
kave however they are working on it uh
to maybe not sure maybe in future
release we we don't see this issue but
this is the currently uh the pinning
issue that we
have okay and the sixth uh thing is the
it is meant for the io intensive
application now as someone was
mentioning um what will happen uh so
this is only give you benefit when you
have like IO intensive application and
this IO intensive application basically
means that your application in doing
blocking calls external blocking calls
be it Database Network calls file right
anything but if you're doing some
inmemory calls right or you if you're
there is like a CPU intensive task then
it is not recommended to use Virtual
thread uh you can just use the your
platform threads and then be done with
it also it's like virtual threads are
not faster than the platform threads but
it just the way it handles is is
optimized than the platform threads so
don't use for the CPU intensive
application and don't use uh in parallel
stream you should not make any um
external call actually in the parallel
stream but uh just calling it
out so yeah that's mostly it any
questions so
far
audience guys online if you have any
question you can ask so uh one question
right so you said uh should not use
should not cash any expensive object so
and also you said thread local we can
use in our right so what kind of so
usually we will cash simple date format
kind of things right so those things can
be cached
right huh so simple date format the
problem with it is basically it's very
expensive object rather you can go with
the date time formet uh in in place uh
which is kind of a
um lightweight object in in place of the
uh simple date format also you can use
the scope
variable uh you can also read about the
scope variable but uh scope variable is
a way to provide so what it does is just
like the thread local thread local give
so basic local provides the objects for
all the threads which is being used
right similarly you can also use scope
variable which givs the
access to those kind of objects which
are required for multiple
threads so that's the uh solution for it
or that's the alternative a better way
to cat the
objects got
it uh here there are more couple
of
um reference link that I have put it
here uh you can go over this one so it
basically talks about the loom proposal
the second preview
the documentation for the loom uh
detailed notes like how what all things
has happened or what all
um things are going on in terms of loom
and and the scope variable that we
discuss structure concurrency and then
you can also read about the spring boot
adoption after spring boot
3.2.0 uh spring boot is adopting two
virtual thread so there's only one flag
that you need to just enable property
and then it will start uh using the
virtual thread under
all Loom related blog you can also read
about this 1 million concurrent
connection and then there's a GitHub
link for this particular demo we'll put
it on on the um YouTube as well for in
the pin comment so you guys can take a
look cool if no question then we can I
have one uh question regarding parel
stream you mentioned that uh we should
not be using it I want to can you
explain more
on that oh parall basically uh okay so
parallel stream if you are using virtual
threads right so those
are par stream what it does it basically
use the uh thread pull
um and when it calls the so virtual
threads is something which makes the
external call right so you mostly use
Virtual thread in order to do a blocking
operation and if you are making a
blocking
operation um
then it it takes
uh it need to understand because it
already understands the the async way of
handling things so if you're using
within the parallel stream it will not
be beneficial you can also read about
the parallel stream not using the um any
kind of external call or the uh doing
things which is required to call the or
external Services I can put a link over
here because like a big question okay
okay thank you
thanks I have one
question second when we
second so how many platform threads 200
how many 200 200 yes so the question was
how many platform thread was used when
we ran the virtual thread example like
when we started to use Virtual threads
so by default underneath tomat uh uses
200 uh but yeah I can also can verify
that but it should be around that
only when we don't use Virtual how
many yeah so default thread pool size is
200 you can also configure it so that's
not the issue
uh
um sorry
hello
hello I think I lost
you uh are you able to hear me yes can
hear you now uh I was asking uh has
virtual threads been adapted I mean uh
you have have any production ready code
which is using virtual threads or it's
too new maybe we have mostly
experimenting and using uh code which is
not in like production but we are
planning to do it uh this
week okay yeah so we already had adopted
the Java
21 uh in couple of project which I'm
like working personally but in terms of
production ready we we're going to do it
uh this week okay okay cor thank
you cool uh I think if no more question
then we can close the
call okay uh so just one announcement uh
so we are organizing the 50th day day
it's going to be our Mega D day we are
targeting the llm related topics to
discuss on the uh that Mega de day uh
it's going to be a one day event so if
you are interested uh you can also
register
or basically it it is there on the
Meetup so feel free to register for
it cool guys uh I really appreciate you
joined uh thank you so much for
joining thank
you